Economists have been exploring people's behavior for hundreds of years: how we make decisions, how we act individually and in groups, how we exchange value. They've studied the institutions that facilitate our trade, like legal systems, corporations, marketplaces. But there is a new, technological institution that will fundamentally change how we exchange value, and it's called the blockchain. Now, that's a pretty bold statement, but if you take nothing else away from this talk, I actually want you to remember that while blockchain technology is relatively new, it's also a continuation of a very human story,
Durante siglos, los economistas han explorado nuestro comportamiento: cómo tomamos decisiones, cómo actuamos individualmente y en colectivos, cómo intercambiamos valor. Han estudiado las instituciones que facilitan el comercio, como los sistemas legales, empresas, mercados. Pero hay una nueva institución tecnológica que cambiará radicalmente cómo intercambiamos valor, y se llama la cadena de bloques. Esto es una afirmación muy atrevida, pero si no se van a quedar con nada más de esta charla de verdad quiero que recuerden que aunque la tecnología de esta cadena es relativamente nueva, también es la continuación de una historia muy humana
and the story is this. As humans, we find ways to lower uncertainty about one another so that we can exchange value. Now, one of the first people to really explore the idea of institutions as a tool in economics to lower our uncertainties about one another and be able to do trade was the Nobel economist Douglass North. He passed away at the end of 2015, but North pioneered what's called "new institutional economics." And what he meant by institutions were really just formal rules like a constitution, and informal constraints, like bribery. These institutions are really the grease that allow our economic wheels to function, and we can see this play out over the course of human history. If we think back to when we were hunter-gatherer economies, we really just traded within our village structure. We had some informal constraints in place,
Y la historia es esta: Como humanos, encontramos formas de disminuir nuestra incertidumbre hacia los demás para poder intercambiar valor. Uno de los primeros en verdaderamente explorar la idea de considerar las instituciones como herramientas económicas para disminuir nuestra incertidumbre hacia los otros y ser capaces de comerciar fue el premio Nobel de economía Douglass North. Falleció a finales del 2015, pero North fue el pionero de la denominada "nueva economía institucional". Y lo que él se refería por instituciones en realidad eran reglas formales como una constitución, y restricciones informales, como los sobornos. Estas instituciones son el motor que permite que nuestra economía funcione y esto se observa a lo largo de la historia de la humanidad. Cuando nuestra economía se sustentaba en la caza-recolección, solo comerciábamos dentro de nuestro asentamiento. Había algunas restricciones informales,
but we enforced all of our trade with violence or social repercussions. As our societies grew more complex and our trade routes grew more distant, we built up more formal institutions, institutions like banks for currency, governments, corporations. These institutions helped us manage our trade as the uncertainty and the complexity grew, and our personal control was much lower. Eventually with the internet, we put these same institutions online. We built platform marketplaces like Amazon, eBay, Alibaba,
pero realizábamos todo nuestro comercio con violencia o mediante repercusiones sociales. A medida que la sociedad se hacía más compleja y las rutas de comercio se ampliaban, creamos instituciones más formales, instituciones como bancos, gobiernos, corporaciones. Estas instituciones ayudaron a organizar el comercio mientras aumentaban la incertidumbre y la complejidad y personalmente controlábamos mucho menos. Actualmente, con el internet, hemos puesto las instituciones en la red. Creamos plataformas de mercado como Amazon, eBay, Alibaba,
just faster institutions that act as middlemen to facilitate human economic activity. As Douglass North saw it,
instituciones más rápidas que actúan como intermediarios que facilitan nuestra actividad económica. Según Douglass North,
institutions are a tool to lower uncertainty so that we can connect and exchange all kinds of value in society. And I believe we are now entering a further and radical evolution of how we interact and trade, because for the first time, we can lower uncertainty not just with political and economic institutions, like our banks, our corporations, our governments, but we can do it with technology alone. So what is the blockchain? Blockchain technology is a decentralized database that stores a registry of assets and transactions across a peer-to-peer network. It's basically a public registry of who owns what and who transacts what. The transactions are secured through cryptography, and over time, that transaction history gets locked in blocks of data that are then cryptographically linked together and secured. This creates an immutable, unforgeable record of all of the transactions across this network. This record is replicated on every computer that uses the network. It's not an app. It's not a company. I think it's closest in description to something like Wikipedia. We can see everything on Wikipedia. It's a composite view that's constantly changing and being updated. We can also track those changes over time on Wikipedia, and we can create our own wikis, because at their core, they're just a data infrastructure. On Wikipedia, it's an open platform that stores words and images and the changes to that data over time. On the blockchain,
las instituciones son una herramienta que disminuye la incertidumbre para que podamos conectar e intercambiar todo tipo de valor en la sociedad. Y yo creo que ahora está empezando una evolución más grande y más radical en la forma en que interactuamos y comerciamos, porque por primera vez, podemos disminuir la incertidumbre no solo mediante instituciones políticas y económicas, como bancos, corporaciones o gobiernos, sino que podemos hacerlo solo con la tecnología. Entonces, ¿qué es la cadena de bloques? La tecnología de la cadena de bloques es una base de datos descentralizada que almacena un registro de activos y transacciones en una red peer-to-peer. Es prácticamente una registro público de quién posee qué y quién gestiona qué. Las transacciones se protegen con criptografía, y el historial de transacciones se guarda en bloques de datos que más tarde se agrupan y protegen mediante criptografía. Esto crea un registro inmutable e infalsificable de todas las transacciones de esta red. El registro se copia en cada ordenador que utiliza la red. No es una aplicación. No es una compañía. Es algo más parecido a Wikipedia En Wikipedia podemos verlo todo. Es una visión compuesta que cambia y se actualiza constantemente. También podemos rastrear estos cambios con el tiempo en Wikipedia, y podemos crear wikis, porque esencialmente, es una infraestructura de datos. En Wikipedia, las palabras e imágenes y las modificaciones realizadas se almacenan en una plataforma abierta. La cadena de bloques,
you can think of it as an open infrastructure that stores many kinds of assets. It stores the history of custodianship, ownership and location for assets like the digital currency Bitcoin, other digital assets like a title of ownership of IP. It could be a certificate, a contract, real world objects, even personal identifiable information. There are of course other technical details to the blockchain, but at its core, that's how it works.
se puede considerar una infraestructura abierta que almacena una variedad de activos. Almacena el historial de custodia, propiedad y ubicación de activos como el dinero digital Bitcoin, otros activos digitales, como el título de propiedad de una IP. Puede ser un certificado, un contrato, objetos físicos, incluso información personal identificable. Por supuesto, hay más detalles técnicos en la cadena de bloques, pero esencialmente, así es como funciona.
It's this public registry that stores transactions in a network and is replicated so that it's very secure and hard to tamper with. Which brings me to my point of how blockchains lower uncertainty and how they therefore promise to transform our economic systems in radical ways. So uncertainty is kind of a big term in economics, but I want to go through three forms of it that we face in almost all of our everyday transactions, where blockchains can play a role. We face uncertainties like not knowing who we're dealing with, not having visibility into a transaction and not having recourse if things go wrong. So let's take the first example, not knowing who we're dealing with. Say I want to buy a used smartphone on eBay. The first thing I'm going to do is look up who I'm buying from. Are they a power user? Do they have great reviews and ratings, or do they have no profile at all? Reviews, ratings, checkmarks: these are the attestations about our identities that we cobble together today and use to lower uncertainty about who we're dealing with. But the problem is they're very fragmented. Think about how many profiles you have. Blockchains allow for us to create an open, global platform on which to store any attestation about any individual from any source. This allows us to create a user-controlled portable identity. More than a profile, it means you can selectively reveal the different attributes about you
Este registro público almacena las transacciones en una red y las copia para que sea completamente seguro y difícil de falsificar. Lo cual me lleva a mi argumento de cómo las cadenas de bloques disminuyen la incertidumbre y cómo por lo tanto prometen transformar el sistema económico de forma radical. Incertidumbre es un término un poco amplio en economía, pero voy a centrarme en tres formas a las que nos enfrentamos en casi todas nuestras transacciones diarias, que las cadenas de bloques pueden cambiar. Nos enfrentamos a incertidumbres como no saber con quien lidiamos, no tener visibilidad en una transacción y no tener un recurso si las cosas no salen bien. Así que tomemos el primer ejemplo, no saber con quien lidiamos. Digamos que quiero comprar un smartphone de segunda mano en eBay. Lo primero que haría es buscar al vendedor a quien voy a comprar. ¿Es un usuario avanzado? ¿Tiene buenas críticas y votos, o no tiene ningún perfil? Críticas, votos, vistos buenos: Todo esto verifica nuestra identidad que construimos juntos hoy y usamos para disminuir la incertidumbre sobre con quien tratamos. Pero el problema es que están muy fragmentadas. Piensen en cuántos perfiles tienen. Las cadenas de bloques nos permiten crear una plataforma global abierta en la que almacenar cualquier verificación sobre cualquier individuo de cualquier fuente. Esto nos permite crear una identidad transferible controlada por los usuarios. Más que un perfil, esto significa poder revelar diferentes atributos de forma selectiva
that help facilitate trade or interaction, for instance that a government issued you an ID, or that you're over 21, by revealing the cryptographic proof that these details exist and are signed off on. Having this kind of portable identity around the physical world and the digital world means we can do all kinds of human trade in a totally new way. So I've talked about how blockchains could lower uncertainty in who we're dealing with. The second uncertainty that we often face is just not having transparency into our interactions. Say you're going to send me that smartphone by mail. I want some degree of transparency. I want to know that the product I bought is the same one that arrives in the mail and that there's some record for how it got to me. This is true not just for electronics like smartphones, but for many kinds of goods and data, things like medicine, luxury goods,
que ayudan a facilitar el comercio o la interacción, como que el gobierno le ha expedido un documento de identidad o que tiene más de 21 años, revelando la prueba criptográfica de que esta información existe y está aprobada. Esta identidad transferible, tanto en el mundo físico como en el digital, nos permite establecer todo tipo de comercio de una forma totalmente nueva. He hablado de cómo las cadenas de bloques podrían disminuir la incertidumbre de con quién tratamos. La segunda incertidumbre bastante habitual es la falta de transparencia en las interacciones. Digamos que me van a enviar un smartphone por correo. Querría tener cierta transparencia. Querría saber que el producto comprado es el mismo que voy a recibir en el correo y que hay algún registro de cómo ha llegado. Este no es solo el caso con dispositivos electrónicos, sino también con muchos tipos de bienes y datos, cosas como medicinas, bienes de lujo,
any kind of data or product that we don't want tampered with. The problem in many companies, especially those that produce something complicated like a smartphone, is they're managing all of these different vendors
cualquier tipo de datos o producto que no queremos que se falsifique. El problema en muchas compañías, especialmente las que producen algo complejo como un smartphone, es que están gestionando a todos estos comerciantes
across a horizontal supply chain. All of these people that go into making a product, they don't have the same database. They don't use the same infrastructure, and so it becomes really hard to see transparently a product evolve over time. Using the blockchain, we can create a shared reality across nontrusting entities. By this I mean all of these nodes in the network do not need to know each other or trust each other, because they each have the ability to monitor and validate the chain for themselves. Think back to Wikipedia. It's a shared database,
en una cadena de suministros horizontal. Todas estas personas involucradas en la producción no tienen la misma base de datos. No utilizan la misma infraestructura, por lo que se hace muy difícil ver un producto evolucionar transparentemente. Con la cadena de bloques, podemos crear una realidad compartida conectando entidades desconfiadas. Con esto me refiero a que los nódulos de esta red no necesitan conocerse el uno al otro o confiar el uno en el otro, porque ambos tienen la capacidad de monitorizar y validar la cadena ellos mismos. Piensen otra vez en Wikipedia. Es una base de datos compartida,
and even though it has multiple readers and multiple writers at the same time, it has one single truth. So we can create that using blockchains. We can create a decentralized database that has the same efficiency of a monopoly without actually creating that central authority. So all of these vendors, all sorts of companies, can interact using the same database without trusting one another. It means for consumers, we can have a lot more transparency. As a real-world object travels along, we can see its digital certificate or token move on the blockchain, adding value as it goes. This is a whole new world in terms of our visibility. So I've talked about how blockchains can lower our uncertainties about identity and how they change what we mean about transparency in long distances and complex trades, like in a supply chain. The last uncertainty that we often face is one of the most open-ended, and it's reneging. What if you don't send me the smartphone? Can I get my money back? Blockchains allow us to write code, binding contracts, between individuals and then guarantee that those contracts will bear out without a third party enforcer. So if we look at the smartphone example, you could think about escrow. You are financing that phone, but you don't need to release the funds until you can verify that all the conditions have been met. You got the phone. I think this is one of the most exciting ways that blockchains lower our uncertainties, because it means to some degree we can collapse institutions and their enforcement. It means a lot of human economic activity can get collateralized and automated, and push a lot of human intervention to the edges, the places where information moves from the real world to the blockchain. I think what would probably floor Douglass North about this use of technology is the fact that the very thing that makes it work, the very thing that keeps the blockchain secure and verified, is our mutual distrust. So rather than all of our uncertainties slowing us down and requiring institutions like banks, our governments, our corporations, we can actually harness all of that collective uncertainty and use it to collaborate and exchange more and faster and more open. Now, I don't want you to get the impression that the blockchain is the solution to everything, even though the media has said that it's going to end world poverty, it's also going to solve the counterfeit drug problem and potentially save the rainforest. The truth is, this technology is in its infancy, and we're going to need to see a lot of experiments take place and probably fail
y aunque tiene múltiples lectores y múltiples colaboradores al mismo tiempo, contiene una sola verdad. Y podemos crear esto con cadenas de bloques. Podemos crear una base de datos dispersa tan eficiente como un monopolio sin crear una autoridad central. Todos estos comerciantes, todo tipo de compañías, pueden interactuar usando la misma base de datos sin confiar el uno en el otro. Para los consumidores esto significa mucha más transparencia. Mientras un objeto físico viaja, podemos ver su certificado digital o prueba moverse en la cadena de bloques, añadiendo valor. En cuanto a visibilidad, esto es un mundo nuevo. Hemos visto cómo las cadenas de bloques pueden reducir la incertidumbre de identidad y cómo pueden cambiar lo que nos referimos por transparencia en comercio complicado y a larga distancia, como en una cadena de suministros. La última incertidumbre a la que nos enfrentamos a menudo es una de las más abiertas, y es el incumplimiento. ¿Qué pasa si no me mandan el smartphone? ¿Me van a devolver el dinero? Las cadenas de bloques nos permiten escribir código, acuerdos vinculantes, entre individuos y más tarde garantizar que el acuerdo se va a cumplir sin la imposición de una tercera persona. Si volvemos al ejemplo del smartphone, podríamos pensar en un fideicomiso. Usted está financiando el teléfono pero no necesita liberar sus fondos antes de verificar el cumplimiento de todas las condiciones. Ya tiene el teléfono. Esta es una de las formas más interesantes en las que las cadenas de bloques disminuyen la incertidumbre, porque en cierto modo podemos colapsar las instituciones y su ejecución. Significa que una gran parte de la actividad económica se puede avalar y automatizar, y llevar una gran parte de la intervención humana a las zonas donde la información se mueve del mundo real a la cadena de bloques. Lo que seguramente dejaría atónito a Douglass North sobre este uso de la tecnología es el hecho que la misma cosa que hace que funcione, la misma cosa que mantiene la seguridad y la verificación de la cadena de bloques, es nuestra desconfianza mutua. Estas incertidumbres no nos frenan, no nos hacen requerir instituciones como bancos, gobiernos, compañías, podemos albergar toda esta incertidumbre colectiva y utilizarla para colaborar e intercambiar más de forma más rápida y abierta. No quiero que tengan la impresión de que la cadena de bloques lo soluciona todo, incluso cuando lo medios han dicho que acabará con la pobreza mundial, y solucionará la falsificación de medicamentos potencialmente salvando la selva. En verdad, esta tecnología está en desarrollo, y vamos a tener que presenciar varios experimentos y posibles fracasos
before we truly understand all of the use cases for our economy. But there are tons of people working on this, from financial institutions to technology companies, start-ups and universities. And one of the reasons is that it's not just an economic evolution. It's also an innovation in computer science. Blockchains give us the technological capability of creating a record of human exchange, of exchange of currency, of all kinds of digital and physical assets, even of our own personal attributes, in a totally new way. So in some ways, they become a technological institution that has a lot of the benefits of the traditional institutions we're used to using in society, but it does this in a decentralized way. It does this by converting a lot of our uncertainties into certainties. So I think we need to start preparing ourselves, because we are about to face a world where distributed, autonomous institutions have quite a significant role. Thank you. (Applause) Bruno Giussani: Thank you, Bettina. I think I understood that it's coming, it offers a lot of potential, and it's complex. What is your estimate for the rate of adoption? Bettina Warburg: I think that's a really good question. My lab is pretty much focused on going the enterprise and government route first, because in reality, blockchain is a complex technology. How many of you actually understand how the internet works? But you use it every day, so I think we're sort of facing the same John Sculley idea of technology should either be invisible or beautiful, and blockchain is kind of neither of those things right now, so it's better suited for either really early adopters who kind of get it and can tinker around or for finding those best use cases like identity or asset tracking or smart contracts that can be used at that level of an enterprise or government. BG: Thank you. Thanks for coming to TED. BW: Thanks. (Applause)
antes de poder entender todos los casos de uso para nuestra economía. Pero hay mucha gente trabajando en ello, desde instituciones financieras hasta compañías tecnológicas, empresas emergentes y universidades. Y una de las razones es que no es solo una evolución económica. También es una innovación informática. Las cadenas de bloques nos dan la capacidad tecnológica de crear un registro de intercambios personales, intercambios monetarios,, de todo tipo de activos digitales y físicos, incluso de nuestros propios atributos, de una forma totalmente nueva. En cierto modo, se convierten en una institución tecnológica que tiene muchas de las ventajas de las instituciones tradicionales a las que estamos acostumbrados pero de una forma descentralizada. Esto se consigue convirtiendo muchas de nuestras incertidumbres en certezas. Así que debemos empezar a prepararnos, porque estamos a punto de conocer un mundo donde las instituciones dispersas y autónomas desempeñarán un papel muy importante. Gracias. (Aplauso) Bruno Giussani: Gracias, Bettina. Creo haber entendido que está llegando, tiene un gran potencial, y es complejo. ¿Cuál es su estimado sobre la tasa de adopción? Bettina Warburg: Esa es una muy buena pregunta. Mi laboratorio se centra en empezar con empresas y el gobierno, porque la cadena de bloques es una tecnología compleja. ¿Cuántos de ustedes entienden cómo funciona el internet? Sin embargo, lo usan a diario, creo que estamos ante la misma idea de John Sculley de que la tecnología debería ser o invisible o bella, y la cadena de bloques no es exactamente ninguna de las dos todavía, así que es más apropiada para usuarios pioneros que la entienden y pueden jugar con ella o para encontrar los casos donde utilizarla como rastrear identidades o activos o contratos inteligentes que pueden usarse a nivel de una empresa o gobierno. BG: Gracias. Gracias por venir a TED. BW: Gracias. (Aplauso)